Guide to the Intelsat Agreement Negotiating History Records, 1961-1998 MS2186
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Intelsat Agreement Negotiating History records
1967-1998
1968-1971
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Telecommunications Satellite Consortium
MS2186
16.25 Linear Feet
This collection focuses on documenting the negotiating history behind the formation and governance of INTELSAT, the International Telecommunications Satellite Organization. Included are documents used in actual meetings, conferences, and working groups, correspondence both internal and external, drafts of various governing documents, technical reports, and position papers of the various countries involved, and finally the official intergovernmental agreements. Also included are vertical files from each election for the position of Director General. Material in the collection dates from 1961-1998, with the majority of the negotiating history records being from 1968-1971. Some of the correspondence and documents have indexes, which are filed at the beginning of each series when present.
Arrangement of Collection
Organized into 7 series: Conference documents, Correspondence, Position papers, Draft agreements, Final documents, Vertical files, Directors' General, and Technical reports
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains documents used in actual meetings, conferences, and working groups, correspondence both internal and external, drafts of various governing documents, technical reports, and position papers of the various countries involved, and finally the official intergovernmental agreements. Also included are vertical files from each election for the position of Director General. Included in the directors' general vertical files is information regarding the dismissal of director Richard Colino. Some of the correspondence and documents have indexes, which are filed at the beginning of each series when present. This collection focuses on documenting the negotiating history behind the formation and governance of INTELSAT, the International Telecommunications Satellite Organization. Dates of the collection are from 1961-1998, though the bulk of this collection dates from 1968-1971, during the negotiations for the definitive agreements of the member nations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was originally gathered through the efforts of John B. Gantt, lead attorney involved in the negotiating process, and William English, a communications scientist and member of the board of COMSAT, the United States Satellite governing body.
It is unknown who donated this collection to the University and in what year.
Historical note
The International Telecommunications Satellite Consortium (Intelsat) was an international organization formed to oversee international satellite communication. Intelsat mangaed communication satellites that provided international broadcast services. The intergovernmental organization began on August 20, 1964 with 11 participating countries. Intelsat's first satellite went into orbit in 1965 and at the time had eleven particpating countries. By 1973, Intelsat had grown to more than 80 countries. In 1971 these 80 countries finally reach an agreement to broaden control of the world's communication satellite system. The INTELSAT Definitive Agreement entered into force on February 12, 1973. Prior to this landmark agreement the United States had been running Intelsat. This agreement provided the United States, represented by Communication Satellite Corp (Comsat), will remain the dominant power in Intelsat. Also, in this agreement no one country will control more than 40% of the votes of the Board of Governors. Intelsat will convene an assembly where all member nations will have equal voices.
By 2001, Intelsat became a private company with the primary source of revenue comign from satellite usage fees. The Intelsat system enables Internet connection, television broadcasting, cellular telephony, and corporate network services.
International Maritime Satellite Organization; Telecommunication; International Communications Satellite Organization; Artificial satellites in telecommunication; Communications Satellite Corporation -- Administration
- Conference documents, 1969 February 20 - 1971 May 17; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents used in actual meetings, plenipotentiary conferences, working groups, and including press releases and agenda. The material dates from 1969-1971 and includes material from the all the committees, negotiating conferences, and intersessional working groups. Beginning with a selected list of conference documents, numbered in their original order, then materials from the committee meetings: Structure and Function, Legal, Financial, and Operational.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by conference.
  - Index and original user guide to Intelsat Definitive Arrangements, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Index of Conference Documents, 1969 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Documents 1-8, 1968 December-1969 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Documents 9-17, 1969 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Summary Record and Orders of the Day, 1969 February - 1969 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases, Informational Documents, 1969 February - 1969 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Structure and Function Committee documents, 1969 February 20 -1969 March 20; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Structure and Function Committee Summary Reports, 1969 March 3- March 20; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal and Procedural Committee documents and summary reports, 1969 March 6 - March 20; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financial Arrangements Committee documents and summary reports, 1969 March 3 - March 20; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Operational Arrangements Committee documents and summary reports, 1969 February 24 - March 20; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Preparatory Committee documents and summary reports, 1969 June 12 - July 14; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Preparatory Committee information and orders of the day, 1969 June 19 - July 11; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Preparatory Committee (II) documents, 1969 August 1 - September 23; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Preparatory Committee (II) summary reports, information, and orders of the day, 1969 August 29 - September 19; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Preparatory Committee (II) Working Group on Financial Questions documents and summary report, 1969 September 2 - September 17; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Preparatory Committee (II) Working Group on Legal Questions documents and summary reports, 1969 September 5 - September 19; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Preparatory Committee (III) documents, 1969 November 7 - December 11; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Preparatory Committee (III) summary reports, information and orders of the day, 1969 November 13 - December 11; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Preparatory Committee (III) Working Group on Financial Questions documents and summary reports, 1969 November 13 - December 11; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Preparatory Committee (III) Working Group on Legal Questions documents and summary reports, 1969 October 30 - November 29; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Plenipotentiary Conference of 1970 documents, 1970 February 27; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Plenipotentiary Conference of 1970 documents folder 2 of 3, 1970 February 17- February 23; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Plenipotentiary Conference of 1970 documents folder 3 of 3, Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Plenipotentiary Conference of 1970 summary records, 1970 February 16 - March 20; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Plenipotentiary Conference of 1970 orders of the day, informational press releases, 1970 February 17 - March 20; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Intersessional Working Group index to documents, 1970 May 29; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Intersessional Working Group documents, 1970 April 28 - June 11; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Intersessional Working Group summary record, 1970 May 18th - June 12; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Intersessional Working Group orders of the day, information, 1970 April 27 - May 20; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Intersessional Working Group Operating Agreement subgroup documents, 1970 June 5- June 10; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 2nd Intersessional Working Group documents, 1970 September 8 - October 9; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 2nd Intersessional Working Group summary reports, 1970 September 8 - October 1; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 2nd Intersessional Working Group orders of the day and information, 1970 August 12 - October 2; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 2nd Intersessional Working Group Operating Agreement subgroup documents, 1970 September 8 - October 12; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 3rd Intersessional Working Group documents index, undated; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 3rd Intersessional Working Group documents, 1970 November 20 - December 14; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 3rd Intersessional Working Group documents, 1970 December 16 - December 30; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 3rd Intersessional Working Group documents: Annexes A-D, 1970 December 30; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 3rd Intersessional Working Group documents: Operating Agreement, 1970 December 30; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Document Index, 1971 May 27; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Documents 149-191, 1971 February 2 - May 7; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Documents 192-231, 1971 8 May - 17 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Documents 232-233, 1971 19 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Documents 234-239, 1971 20 May - 21 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Summary Record 38-63, 1971 14 April - 27 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Committee A Documents and Summary Records, 1971 19 April - 8 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Committee B Documents and Summary Records, 1971 19 April - 7 May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Orders of the Day, Information, Press Releases, 1971 14 April - 21 May; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1971 Plenipotentiary Conference Committee B Draft texts and edits, 1971 16 April - 17 May; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1961 January - 1971 December; Series 2
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series begins with an chronological index for the correspondence. Material dates from 1961-1971. Included are many internal communications from the Communications Satellite Corp. (COMSAT), also included are communications to and with the U.S. Department of State. Correspondents include among others, John B. Gantt (Hunton and Williams, LLC), William D. English, Ambassador Abbott Washburn, (chair of the US delegation), Joseph Charyk (President, COMSAT), Richard Mizrack, David Acheson.
  - Chronological index to correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1961 correspondence, Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1962-1963 correspondence, 1962 January - 1963 December; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1964 correspondence, Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    General
    No correspondence exists for 1965.
  - 1966 January-May correspondence, Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1966 June correspondence, Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1966 June-July correspondence, 1966 June 24-25; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 1966 July correspondence, progress reports 1 and 2, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1966 December correspondence, progress report 3, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1967 correspondence and progress report 4, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1968 correspondence, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1969 January correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1969 January correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1969 February correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1969 February correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1969 March correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1969 March correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1969 April correspondence, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1969 May correspondence, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1969 June correspondence, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1969 July correspondence, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1969 August correspondence, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1969 September correspondence, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1969 October correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1969 October correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1969 November correspondence, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1969 December correspondence, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 1970 January correspondence (folder 1 of 3), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1970 January correspondence (folder 2 of 3), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1970 January (folder 3 of 3), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1970 February correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1970 February correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1970 March correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1970 March correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1970 April correspondence (folder 1 of 3), 1970 March; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1970 April correspondence (folder 2 of 3), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1970 April correspondence (folder 3 of 3), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1970 May correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 1970 May correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1970 June correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 1970 June correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 1970 July correspondence, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 1970 August correspondence (1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1970 August correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1970 September correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1970 September correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1970 October correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1970 October correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1970 November correspondence (folder 1 of 2), 1970 October; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1970 November correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1970 December correspondence, Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1971 January correspondence, Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 1971 February correspondence, Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1971 March correspondence, Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 1971 April correspondence (folder 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 1971 April correspondence (folder 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1971 May correspondence, Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1971 June correpondence, Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 1971 July correspondence, Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - 1971 August correspondence, Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - 1971 September-December correpondence, 1971 September 1 - 1971 December 31; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Position papers, 1968 March - 1970 December and undated; Series 3
  In this series the"By Subject" position papers are arranged alphabetically by the major topics of discussion throughout the conference negotiations. These topics include Accession, Board of Governors, Membership, and Liability and Legal issues. "By country" position papers contain information on how each country contributed to the negotiations, issues, and how they voted on issues. Most of this intelligence was gathered by COMSAT, the United States satellite governing body, and these materials date from 1968-1971 (and undated). Please note that country labels reflect nation names from that time period.
  Arranged in 2 subseries: Subject position papers and Country position papers.
  - Subject position papers, 1968 March - 1970 December and undated; Series 3 subseries 1
    In this subseries the "By Subject" position cover the major topics of discussion throughout the conference negotiations. These topics include Accession, Board of Governors, Membership, and Liability and Legal issues.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - By Subject: Accession, 1968 November 12; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - By Subject: Amendments, Arbitration, 1969 January 27 and undated; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - By Subject: Assembly, Board of Governors, Customs, Data, Financial Arrangements, Functional Competence, Investment, 1969 February - May and undated; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - By Subject: Legal Issues, Legal Status, 1968 November -1969 July and undated; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - By Subject: Liability, Manager, 1969 January - 1969 August; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - By Subject: Membership, Major Organs, Conference Participants, Privilege and Immunity, Procurement, 1968 November - 1969 May and undated; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - By Subject: Regional Systems, Rules of Procedure, 1968 December - 1969 May; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - By Subject: Scope, Taxation, Terms and conditions, Transition, Treaty and Withdrawal, 1968 March - 1970 December and undated; Series 3 subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Country position papers, 1968 March - 1970 December and undated; Series 3 subseries 2
    The "By country" position papers contain information on how each country contributed to the negotiations, issues, and how they voted on issues. Please note that country labels reflect nation names from that time period.
    - By Country: Algeria, Argentina, Austria, Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, 1969 July - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - By Country: Ceylon, Chile, China, Columbia, Denmark, Ethiopia, France, F.R. Germany, 1969 April - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - By Country: Greece, Guatemala, India, Indonesia, Iran, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Jamaica, Japan, Jordan, Kenya, 1969 April - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - By Country: Korea, Kuwait, Lebanon, Liechtenstein, Luxembourg, Malaysia, Mexico, Monaco, Morocco, Netherlands, New Zealand, Nicaragua, Nigeria, Norway, Pakistan, Panama, 1969 April - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - By Country: Peru, Phillipines, Portugal, Saudi Arabia, Singapore, South Africa, Spain, Sudan, Sweden, Switzerland, Syria, 1969 April - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - By Country: Tanzania, Thailand, Tunisia, Turkey, Uganda, United Arab Republic, United Kingdom, Vatican City, Venezuela, Yemen, 1969 April - September and undated; Series 3 subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Draft agreements, 1969 January - 1971 February; Series 4
  This series contains various drafts of the agreements or portions of the agreements, some with handwritten markups. The series is divided into the Operating Agreement drafts, and the Intergovernmental Agreement drafts. Material dates from 1968-1971. One legal-size folder, an Intergovernmental Agreement draft dated February 3, 1970, has been transferred to Box 33 due to its size.
  - Operating Agreement drafts January - February 1969, 1969 January 15- 1969 February 21; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts February - July 1969, 1969 February 27 - 1969 July 23; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts July - Sept. 1969, 1969 July 23 - 1969 September 3; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts September - December 1969, 1969 September 18 - 1969 December 12; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts January - February 1970, 1970 January 6- 1970 February 5; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts February - March 1970, 1970 February 7 - 1970 March 6; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts March-June 1970, 1970 March 9 - 1970 June 12; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts July - September 1970, 1970 July 31 - 1970 September 29; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts December 1970, 1970 December 2; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts December 1970, 1970 December 12; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts December 1970, 1970 December 16; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts February 1971, 1971 February 8; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts February 1971, 1971 February 16 - 1971 February 18; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Operating Agreement Drafts February 1971, 1971 February 19; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Operating Agreement Draft April 1971, 1971 April 1; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement Drafts 1968-January 1969, 1968 September 9 - 1969 January 31; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement Drafts February 1969, 1969 February 8; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement Drafts February - June 1969, 1969 February 21 - 1969 June 24; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement draft July 1969, 1969 July 4; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts July 1969, 1969 July 31; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts September- October 1969, 1969 September 18 - 1969 October 6; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts October 1969, 1969 October 19; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts November 1969, 1969 November 11; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts December 1969, 1969 December 3- 1969 December 11; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February-March 1970 (additional oversize folder), 1970 February 23 - 1970 March 2; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts March 1970, 1970 March 16 - 1970 March 31; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts April-May 1970, 1970 April 23 - 1970 May 21; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts August-October 1970, 1970 August 25 - 1970 October 7; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts October 1970 (1 of 2), 1970 October 28; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts October 1970 (2 of 2), 1970 October 28; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts December 1970, 1970 December 14; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts December 1970, 1970 December 22 - 1970 December 31; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 1971 (1 of 4), 1971 February 2; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 1971 (2 of 4), 1971 February 2; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 1971 (3 of 4), 1971 February 2; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 1971 (4 of 4), 1971 February 2; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement, Draft February 3, 1970, 1970 February 3; Series 4 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 6 1971, 1971 February 6; Series 4 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Intergovernmental Agreement drafts February 8 1971, 1971 February 8; Series 4 (Box 23, Folder 2)